Guide to the William Upcott, Letters and Portraits
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Letters and portraits of eminent persons]
1824-1825
OSBORN D51
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.24
(1 volume)
Autograph MSS. Collection of autograph letters and portraits, mainly of 18th and 19th century literary figures, formed by Anne Nichols (also a collector) for William Upcott; many of the letters are accompanied by engraved portraits of either the writers or recipients.
Upcott, William, 1779-1845
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a partial inventory of the contents of Osborn d51. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Autographs -- Great Britain; Women authors; Upcott, William, 1779-1845
- Osborn d51
  - ALLAN, GEORGE
    - ALS to [?John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1816 Apr 17 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      St. James Park
      2 p.; 19 x 14 cm.
      Concerns the history of Durham and
      Robert Hutchinson (b. 1750).
      d.51/105
  - BEXLEY, NICHOLAS VANSITTART, 1ST BARON, 1766-1851
    - ALS to unnamed recipient, 1811 Sep 9 (Box 1)
      Coombelodge near Reading
      Asks the recipient to mention his
      name to a "Mr. Manning."
      1 p.; 16 x 18 cm.
      d.51/74
  - HARDINGE, GEORGE, 1743-1816
    - AL in 3rd person to Edward Thurlow, 1st baron (1731-1806), n.d. (Box 1)
    - Great Ormonde Street 1 p.; 22 x 19 cm. Invitation to dinner. d.51/61 (Box 1)
  - MORGAN, JOHN R.
    - ALS to Mary Ann Nichols, 1870 Jan 27 (Box 1)
      Norwich
      4 p.; 16 x 10 cm.
      Concerning the sale of the autographs
      of William Upcott (1779-1845).
      d.51/106
  - PARKES, SAMUEL, 1761-1825
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1817 Feb 7 (Box 1)
      Goswell Street
      1 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Letter in behalf of Arthur Aikin
      (1773-1854) who is applying as
      Secretary of Arts.
      d.51/1
  - PARR, SAMUEL, 1747-1825
    - ALS to John Nichols (1745-1826), [no yr] Sep 28 (Box 1)
      n.p.
      2 p.; 16 x 10 cm.
      Invitation to dine.
      d.51/2
  - PARRY, SIR WILLIAM EDWARD, 1790-1855
    - Signature, on fragment of a letter, 1818 Jan 29 (Box 1)
      Craven St., Strand
      1 p.; 7 x 12 cm.
      d.51/3
  - PATON, GEORGE, 1721-1807
    - ALS to Richard Gough (1735-1809), 1798 Nov 30 (Box 1)
      Edinburgh
      1 p.; 25 x 21 cm.
      Concerns the catalogues of upcoming
      book sales in which Gough has
      apparently expressed interest.
      d.51/4
  - PECK, FRANCIS, 1692-1743
    - ALS to Joseph Ames (1689-1759), 1740 Feb 22 (Box 1)
      Godeby
      1 p.; 28 x 21 cm.
      Concerns a letter, to Dr. Thomas
      Deacon (1697-1753), which Peck
      worries has been lost in post.
      d.51/5
  - PEGGE, SAMUEL, 1704-1796
    - ALS to Richard Gough (1735-1809), 1788 Mar 10 (Box 1)
      Whittington
      2 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
      Presents his regrets on the death of
      Mrs. John Nichols as well as
      inquiring about personal matters.
      d.51/6/a
  - PEGGE, SAMUEL, 1704-1796
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1788 Mar 1 (Box 1)
      [Whittington]
      1 p.; 16 x 11 cm.
      Sends his condolences.
      d.51/6/b
  - PERCEVAL, SPENCER, 1762-1812
    - ALS to [?John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1802 Mar 24 (Box 1)
      Lincoln's Inn Fields
      2 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Concerns his interest in books,
      apparently in Nichols's stock.
      d.51/8
  - POLWHELE, RICHARD, 1760-1838
    - ALS to John Nichols (1745-1826), 1818 Jan 16 (Box 1)
      Truro
      3 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Offering copies of his works for
      stock.
      d.51/11
  - POPE, JANE, 1742-1818
    - ALS to unnamed recipient, n.d. (Box 1)
      1 p.; 6 x 17 cm.
      Poem with a note explaining why the
      lines are tardy.
      d.51/13,14
  - POPHAM, SIR HOME RIGGS, 1762-1820
    - ALS to Mr. Pearce, [?1806] (Box 1)
      [Buenos Ayres]
      2 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
      Short description of current events
      on a ship with a French general and
      American captain; in another hand on
      verso of last leaf of letter, a
      short description of Popham's
      accomplishments.
      d.51/15
  - PORSON, RICHARD, 1759-1808
    - Signature, on an engraved form acknowledging receipt of a book from Joseph Adams (1756-1818), 1808 Jul 12 (Box 1)
      London
      1 p.; 8 x 12 cm.
      d.51/16
  - PORTEUS, BEILBY, BP. OF LONDON, 1731-1808
    - ALS to Richard Gough (1735-1809), 1801 May 1 (Box 1)
      St. James's Square
      Responds to an inquiry.
      d.51/17
  - PRETYMAN-TOMLINE, SIR GEORGE, BP. OF WINCHESTER, 1750-1827
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1785 Oct 5 (Box 1)
      Gt. George Street
      3 p.; 24 x 19 cm.
      Concerns the recipient's brother.
      d.51/18
  - REED, ISAAC, 1742-1807
    - ALS to [?John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1778 (Box 1)
      Staple Inn
      3 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Complains of the ill treatment of
      Thomas Cadell (1742-1802).
      d.51/21
  - REES, ABRAHAM, 1743-1825
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1824 May 24 (Box 1)
      Finsbury
      1 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      Concerns autographs of his "literary
      correspondents".
      d.51/22
  - RENNELL, THOMAS, 1754-1840
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1825 Feb 2 (Box 1)
      Winchester
      Requests a paper copy and plates of
      "British Monachism" by Thomas Dudley
      Fosbroke (1770-1842) as well as the
      advertised illustrations for
      Fosbroke's "Encyclopaedia of
      Antiquities".
      d.51/23
  - RENNIE, JOHN, 1761-1821
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1808 Jun 17 (Box 1)
      Stamford St.
      1 p.; 19 x 12 cm.
      Concerns a package which he presumes
      contains books and articles which he
      ordered.
      d.51/24
  - ROGERS, SAMUEL, 1763-1855
    - Signature, with two specimens of his hand., 1819 Jan 7 (Box 1)
      St. James's Place
      d.51/25
  - ROSCOE, WILLIAM, 1753-1831
    - ALS to John McCreery (1768-1832), 1821 Dec 17 (Box 1)
      Holkham
      1 p.; 19 x 17 cm.
      Discusses his corrections of a
      manuscript proof.
      d.51/26
  - ROSE, GEORGE, 1744-1818
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1811 May 8 (Box 1)
      Old Palace Yard
      Inquires about Bacon's works.
      d.51/27
  - SAUMAREZ, JAMES SAUMAREZ, 1ST BARON, 1757-1836
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1819 Jan 7 (Box 1)
      Guernsey
      2 p.; 20 x 12 cm.
      Requests that Nichols forward
      information for Sir Henry Blackwood
      (1770-1832).
      d.51/29
  - SCHOMBERG, ISAAC, 1714-1780
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1744 Jun 26 (Box 1)
      Wells
      1 p.; 15 x 15 cm.
      A brief word about his present
      literary project.
      d.51/30
  - SHARP, GRANVILLE, 1735-1813
    - ALS to Joseph Plymley, later Corbett (ca. 1760-1830), 1794 Jul 17 (Box 1)
      Garden Court
      1 p.; 22 x 18 cm.
      Concerns the anti-slavery movement.
      d.51/35
  - SHARP, THOMAS, 1770-1841
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1809 Mar 16 (Box 1)
      Coventry
      A case of arbitration.
      d.51/36
  - SHERLOCK, THOMAS, BP. OF LONDON, 1678-1761
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1748/9 Feb 11 (Box 1)
      Temple
      2 p.; 22 x 17 cm.
      Concerns papers sent to him by the
      correspondent.
      d.51/39
  - SHIELD, WILLIAM, 1748-1829
    - ALS to [?John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1824 May 7 (Box 1)
      31 Berners St.
      1 p.; 17 x 12 cm.
      Presents his regrets to an
      invitation to the anniversary of
      the Literary Fund.
      d.51/40
  - SMALRIDGE, GEORGE, BP. OF BRISTOL, 1663-1719
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, n.d. (Box 1)
      1 p.; 19 x 15 cm.
      Discusses his imminent trip to
      Windsor and his present colleagues.
      d.51/44
  - SMITH, JOHN THOMAS, 1766-1833
    - ALS to Anne Nichols, 1824 Mar 4 (Box 1)
      British Museum
      1 p.; 25 x 19 cm.
      Presents a page to the collection of
      autographs.
      d.51/48
  - SPENCER, JOHN CHARLES SPENCER, 3RD EARL, 1782-1845
    - AL in 3rd person to John Nichols (1745-1826), 1816 May 25 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 23 x 17 cm.
      Discusses recent orders from Messrs
      Nichols Son and Bentley.
      d.51/50
  - STAMFORD, GEORGE HARRY GREY, 5TH EARL OF, 1737-1819
    - AL in 3rd person to John Nichols (1745-1826), 1815 Mar 6 (Box 1)
      Enville [Staffs.]
      1 p.; 24 x 20 cm.
      Accompanied by another note, 6 x 15
      cm.; both letters order books.
      d.51/51
  - STEEVENS, GEORGE, 1736-1800
    - ALS to John Nichols (1745-1836), [1784] (Box 1)
      1 p.; 8 x 10 cm.
      Concerns the funeral of Samuel
      Johnson (1709-1784).
      d.51/54
  - STRUTT, JOSEPH, 1749-1802
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1836)], 1802 May 8 (Box 1)
      Charles Street, Hatton Garden
      Concerns the settlement of an
      outstanding bill.
      d.51/55
  - TANNER, JOHN, 1684-1759
    - ALS to Joseph Ames (1689-1759), 1744 Apr 7 (Box 1)
      Lowestoft
      1 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
      Sends a manuscript for consideration.
      d.51/58
  - THICKNESSE, PHILIP, 1719-1792
    - Essay on William Dodd (1729-1777): autograph MS, initialled, n.d. (Box 1)
      4 p.; 24 x 18 cm. and 1 p.; 15 x
      10 cm.
      d.51/58a,59
  - THROSBY, JOHN, 1740-1803
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1836)], 1800 Mar 24 (Box 1)
      [Leicester]
      1 p.; 22 x 16 cm.
      Concerns the Sacheverell family.
      d.51/60
  - THURLOW, EDWARD THURLOW, 1ST BARON, 1731-1806
    - ALS to John Bowyer Nichols (1779-1863), 1824 Apr 13 (Box 1)
      Brighton
      Discusses his recent translation of
      Horace.
      d.51/62
  - TICKELL, THOMAS, 1686-1740
    - ALS to Mr. Worsley, 1721 May 30 (Box 1)
      Whitehall
      Discusses his payment of a bill.
      d.51/63
  - TILLOCH, ALEXANDER, 1759-1825
    - ALS to John Nichols (1745-1836), 1816 Nov 15 (Box 1)
      Star Office
      1 p.; 24 x 19 cm.
      Introduces a Dr. Henderson to Mr.
      Nichols.
      d.51/64
  - TODD, HENRY JOHN, 1763-1845
    - AL in 3rd person to Anne Nichols, [no yr] Jul 19 (Box 1)
      Coulsdon
      1 p.; 21 x 18 cm.
      Presents two autographs for the
      collection.
      d.51/65
  - TOMKINS, THOMAS, 1743-1816
    - ALS to James Asperne, 1816 May 12 (Box 1)
      Sermon Lane
      Declines a request for a favor.
      d.51/66
  - TOOKE, WILLIAM, 1744-1820
    - ALS to John Nichols (1745-1836), 1788 Aug 25 (Box 1)
      St. Petersburg
      Corrections and thoughts on a
      pamphlet he has sent to Nichols for
      review.
      d.51/68
  - TOOKE, WILLIAM, 1744-1820
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1819 Mar 11 (Box 1)
      Ormond St.
      1 p.; 9 x 19 cm.
      Fragment of a letter, perhaps a
      letter of condolence.
      d.51/69
  - TOOKE, WILLIAM, 1744-1820
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1836)], n.d. (Box 1)
      1 p.; 10 x 19 cm.
      Fragment; inquires about the
      family's health.
      d.51/69a
  - TRIMMER, SARAH (KIRBY), 1741-1810
    - ALS to Joseph Plymley, later Corbett (ca. 1760-1830), 1798 Aug 23 (Box 1)
      Brentford
      2 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Thanks the recipient for his
      interest in the new edition of "The
      Day School Spelling Book."
      d.51/70
  - TURNER, DAWSON, 1775-1858
    - ALS to Anne Nichols, 1824 Dec 15 (Box 1)
      Yarmouth
      Reply to her order for some etchings.
      d.51/71
  - UPCOTT, WILLIAM, 1779-1845
    - ALS to Anne Nichols, 1823 Oct 19 (Box 1)
      London Institution
      Reply to a dinner invitation.
      d.51/78
  - VINCENT, WILLIAM, 1739-1815
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1808 Nov 25 (Box 1)
      Deanery, Westminster
      Requests the return of his books.
      d.51/77
  - WAKEFIELD, GILBERT, 1756-1807
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1789 Oct 2 (Box 1)
      Nottingham
      Complaint about a reviewer.
      d.51/79
  - WARBURTON, WILLIAM, BP. OF GLOUCESTER, 1698-1779
    - Memorandum for "The Divine Legation of Moses": autograph MS (Box 1)
      3 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
      Possibly an emendation intended for
      a revised edition of the work.
      d.51/81
  - WARE, JAMES, 1756-1815
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], n.d. (Box 1)
      1 p.; 18 x 12 cm.
      Reply to an invitation.
      d.51/82
  - WARTON, JOSEPH, 1722-1800
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1783 Jun 7 (Box 1)
      Discusses a recent work.
      d.51/83
  - WARTON, THOMAS, 1728-1790
    - ALS to Richard Gough, 1782 Sep 22 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 30 x 20 cm.
      Discusses corrections for an
      imminent publication.
      d.51/85
  - WATHEN, JAMES, 1751-1828
    - ALS to [?Anne Nichols], 1825 Jan 1 (Box 1)
      Hereford
      3 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Sends his portrait with the letter.
      d.51/86
  - WATSON, RICHARD, BP. OF LLANDAFF, 1737-1816
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1804 Dec 19 (Box 1)
      Calgarth Park
      Requests that his order be sent.
      d.51/87
  - WHALLEY, PETER, 1722-1791
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1786 Jun 2 (Box 1)
      St. Olave's School
      2 p.; 25 x 19 cm.
      Answer to inquiries made by Nichols
      in previous correspondence.
      d.51/90
  - WHITAKER, THOMAS DUNHAM, 1759-1821
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1803 Sep 22 (Box 1)
      Holme
      Inquires about a proof sheet he sent
      previously.
      d.51/91
  - WHITBREAD, SAMUEL, 1758-1815
    - ALS to John Nichols (1745-1826), 1791 Jul 28 (Box 1)
      Tonbridge
      d.51/92
  - WHITE, JOSEPH, 1745-1814
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1788 Jan 30 (Box 1)
      Oxford
      3 p.; 22 x 18 cm.
      Asks Nichols to complete the
      printing of his new study of Arabic
      and Latin types.
      d.51/94
  - WILBERFORCE, WILLIAM, 1759-1833
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1803 Dec 29 (Box 1)
      Clapham
      2 p.; 18 x 13 cm.
      Returns his proxy.
      d.51/96
  - WILBERFORCE, WILLIAM, 1759-1833
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, [1804?] May 5 (Box 1)
      2 p.; 24 x 19 cm.
      Discusses an attempt to see William
      Pitt (1759-1806) at Downing Street.
      d.51/97
  - WILLIAMS, DAVID, 1738-1814
    - ALS to John Calder (1733-1815), 1789 Feb 4 (Box 1)
      Gt. Russell St.
      Informs Calder of his temporary
      illness.
      d.51/99
  - WILLIS, BROWNE, 1682-1760
    - ALS to Richard Grey (1694-1771), 1734 Oct 10 (Box 1)
      Whadden
      1 p.; 19 x 18 cm.
      Informs him of his health and other
      family matters.
      d.51/100
  - WILKIE, SIR DAVID, 1785-1841
    - ALS to Robert Balmanno, 1819 Apr 19 (Box 1)
      Lower Phillimore Place
      1 p.; 17 x 18 cm.
      d.51/101
  - WODHULL, MICHAEL, 1740-1816
    - ALS to [?John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1795 May 3 (Box 1)
      Old Hummums, Covent Garden
      Desires to be placed on a list of
      subscribers.
      d.51/102
  - WOODFALL, WILLIAM, 1746-1803
    - ALS to [John Nichols (1745-1826)], 1785 Oct 4 (Box 1)
      Dorset St.
      Returns a copy of "Biographical
      Anecdotes" by William Bowyer
      (1699-1777) and requests a sketch.
      d.51/103
  - WRANGHAM, FRANCIS, 1769-1842
    - ALS to John Nichols (1745-1826), 1815 May 29 (Box 1)
      Hunmanby
      1 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Inquires whether a collection of
      books he has just purchased
      previously belonged to William
      Bowyer (1699-1777).
      d.51/104